Ta-da! So, where am I now?
Oh! Some of you got it right! So I am here in Onaga Bay today!
Yes, it's been a while since I've been here, like 5 or 6 years, but I've been able to interact with the people of Onaga Bay.
It's been about 5 or 6 years since I've been here, but since the disaster, I've been in touch with the people of Onaga Bay.
I have been in touch with the people of Onaga Bay since the disaster, and we have become friends.
It's been a long time since I've been able to come to Onagawamachi due to the Corona and other reasons.
But today, I came to see my friend after a long absence!
The last time I was here, the pine trees themselves were already in place, but I thought they were even more beautiful.
The pine trees themselves were already here when I was here last time, but the place has become even more beautiful, and I think the number of stores has increased.
So, I would like to enjoy the new Onaga Bay Town that has evolved even further.
Today, I would like to stroll around the town while asking the staff of the tourist association about various things!
So, who will be there?
Ta-da!
It's been a while! I'm back!
I've become a member of the tourist association.
When did you get here?
When did I get here?
You're the fish cake shop, right?
It was supposed to be a fish paste shop.
That's right.
We're going to work together on town projects.
I'm the vice president of the Onaga Tourist Association.
I'm Yuki Takahashi. Pleased to meet you.
Pleased to meet you.
In the five or six years that you were away from us, did anything concrete change at Onaga Station itself?
What exactly has changed at Onaga station in the 5 or 6 years since we missed you?
As I said, the station is still in the same condition as it is now.
The station is still in the same state.
The people who use the station a lot are tourists.
We have a lot of tourists who use the station, and we also have a lot of tourists who use the station.
Also, there are many more stores in town.
And the town is full of color.
Indeed! It's a very lively town.
Onaga-cho is said to be a fishing town.
But when you see how well everyone is doing business
I think it's a commercial town.
There are so many delicious foods here.
There are many restaurants that convey that kind of charm.
Also, I was wondering...
I was thinking, don't stores open early?
Don't they open early?
We arrived in Onaga-cho this morning.
There are a lot of stores that open at 9:00 or 10:00 a.m.
Isn't 9 o'clock normal?
It's not that common.
Our Kawaniwa Garden opens at 8:30.
Really?
What kind of restaurant is Onaga?
That's Okase-san, right?
We used to work with him.
They serve breakfast set menus in the morning.
Wow!
They serve salmon roe on rice in the morning.
You might say, "That's enough!
It's so extravagant!
Is that what they're trying to collect?
Yes, the auction starts around 6:00 a.m. at the morning market.
That's right, the auction starts around 6:00 a.m. at the market, so we can get them fresh.
When you think about it, it's really amazing, isn't it?
When we first visited Onagamachi, it was right after the disaster.
It was really right after the disaster, right after the earthquake.
There was a lot of rubble and debris.
The sea and debris.
Right on the beach.
There was no other place to eat, but there was a seafood bowl restaurant.
That's where we ate.
I still remember that.
Yes, I remember.
It was impressive.
I had never seen such a scene before.
I had never seen anything like this.
Of course I thought so from the TV images, but
but when I actually came here, I felt it even more, I really felt it.
What really impressed me there was
I'm sure that the situation is still not at all what it used to be.
In the midst of such a difficult situation
They were so hospitable to us.
The happiest thing for us is that they eat our food.
He also said that he was happy that we could come to the restaurant like this.
His words really saved my life.
They cheered me up.
I understand. I understand.
But it's been five years.
That's right.
Welcome back.
I'm back.
A lot has changed. I'll show you around.
I look forward to working with you today.
Thank you very much.
Where would you like to go first?
Yes.
Well, people tend to focus on the upper gate of Onaga-cho.
But of course, there are people who live here.
Before the earthquake, the population was 10,000, but now it is less than 6,000.
Wow.
Even so, the sound of children's cheerful voices playing together is still a source of great relief for us.
It is a tremendous source of relief for us.
So we decided that we had to create such a place.
That's why they built a park on the seashore.
Oh, I see.
There wasn't a park before, was there?This park didn't exist before.
What is this? It's like, "What is this?
There is something wonderful about the ocean in the city.
The countryside has the beauty of the sea, because if you look there, you can see the boats lined up in a row.
You can see the boats lined up in a row over there.
That's the Mima Line.
Oh, there it is, the samba line.
The lights are so bright and shiny.
It says "fish lights" on the island.
Wow.
That's a samba torufin.
Because we have participated in a kind of three horse festival.
We dance the Samba Dance.
They were dancing.
Wow, it's a park.
Isn't it very rare to see a park like this?
A park like this.
When I think of a park, I think of seesaws and swings.
But this is the first time I've been to a park that doesn't have playground equipment.
This is the first time for a park to have playground equipment.
For example, this is a sea cow.
It's a sea cow.
A sea cow?
What is a sea cow?
It's a playground equipment based on the difficult animals in the sea, such as amebas and ameflagellates, which are found in the sea.
It is a playground equipment based on the motif of them.
Wow.
And, from this side, you can see...
One side of it is a slide.
Wow! Looks like fun!
And the slides are in order, right?
You line up, go down, the next kid goes down, and the next kid goes up, and the next kid goes down, and the next kid goes down, and the next kid goes down.
But there is no time to wait in line here.
Everyone lined up in a row.
Oh my God, it looks so fun. I want to ski so much.
It's fun.
They said they were going to line up here, too.
Oh, man, it's too hard now that I'm an adult.
It's too tight.
Ouch! Where? Where are you coming from?
From this direction, mostly children, yes, yes, yes, like that.
Ha-ha-ha-ha.
Let's go, let's go.
Ha-ha-ha-ha. Oh, no. Oh, no. Kids are amazing.
But make sure it's made of soft material so they don't get hurt.
That's right. And non-slip material.
See....
Ha-ha-ha.
This is scary. It's pretty scary.
Can I slide down this?
Let's go, let's go.
Ha-ha-ha-ha.
Scary!
Wait!
Aaahhh!
A-ha-ha-ha!
Scary!
What is this surrealistic video!
No! I can't be an adult! It's scary!
I'm thinking that even though you're married, you're still trying so hard to meet these challenges.
I'm impressed with you! It's fun!
About five of us here, the kids line up side by side, and we all skate together in a row.
But wow, that's fun!
And you follow this circle like this, right?
That's right, you put your feet up on them and climb up.
I got it!
Dangerous!
Fun!
Welcome to Onaga!
Onaga, I love it!
Wanna go again?
Xonaga!
Let's go that way too!
This is another way to get the kids up to the top without any waiting time.
Once they get up there, they can ski in any direction they want.
It's true!
There's a lot of different directions.
Wow!
And it's pretty high up, so...
You can see all of Onagawa...
You can see all around!
Here we go.
Three, two, one.
Bungy!
I'm getting the hang of it.
You sound just like the kids in Onagawa!
I went down the slide for the first time in years!
How cute! It's nice!
You can sit down and rest.
Mothers, you should bring your kids here.
and just let them sit there and play.
It's like that, isn't it?
And over there is an iron bar.
This is made in the motif of a chin sea eel.
It's made in the motif of a chin sea eel.
What are you going to play with it with? You think.
It's the first thing I didn't know.
I haven't decided what to use it for.
You haven't decided?You haven't decided?
It's just an ordinary iron bar.
But with the slide and the tunnel...
Kids have a lot of ideas and play with them.
Like, "This is a slide, so you should slide down it," or "This is a sandbox, so you should play in the sand.
This is a sandbox, so they should play in the sand.
It's not like that. Children can play as they like.
Some parts are slippery and some parts are not.
or "devise this or that" or "devise this or that" or "devise this or that".
You make up your own rules.
Kids play on their own.
That's what we cherish about this park.
This is amazing!
This?
Pole dancing.
Sexy.
Sexy where the kids are playing.
No, but when you really think about it.
There's a lot of ingenuity going on here.
It's a new kind of park, isn't it?
Yes, it is.
It's unconventional.
With that kind of free thinking
I hope that female children will grow up with such free thinking.
That's great.
What else is new?
Well, let's go into town.
You haven't been there, have you?
No, I haven't.
Not since the earthquake.
The buildings that collapsed during the tsunami...
As they were.
That's the only thing left standing in Onaga.
I see. It's still there.
The old watch tower in Onaga
The current industrial guard in Onaga-cho is in front of the station.
But in the case of the earthquake, it was over here.
A watch tower is very strong, you know.
Because it's sturdy.
Even if it was next to a vertical building
It still hasn't fallen apart.
That's true.
Is this left as is on purpose?
Yes, it is.
Wow.
What's going on here?
It's the building that collapsed in March 2011.
After that, we left it to see what would happen to this place.
So trees have grown up and the grass is still there.
This is what it looked like. It has collapsed.
It should have fallen over there, but it fell on the side.
So, just by looking at the tsunami, you can see the relationship between the direction of the tsunami and the ocean.
You can see how much the tsunami was flowing in relation to the direction of the ocean, and the force of the tsunami.
There is a passageway here, so let's take a look.
Let's take a closer look.
But....
I am sure that people in areas that were not actually affected by the disaster still have these things.
My son is 9 years old and was born after the earthquake. It is a strange feeling for me.
There is also a panel in the toolbox that shows the process of our recovery.
You can see this kind of thing all the time.
And how did we work so hard after the disaster to get to the other side?
You can see how we worked hard afterwards.
This was right after the earthquake, wasn't it?
Yes, that's right.
So this is the ocean. You can see that the tsunami went through the peninsula from this side.
Seeing it in a photograph is one thing, but seeing it in person makes it even more impactful. Yes, that's right. When you look inside, it is a bit more vivid.
At that time. Yes, yes.
There is a telephone hanging from the top. Really.
That's the phone that was used in the police box. So it has been exposed to the rain for 12 years, and the phone may fall down as it deteriorates, but that is also a force of nature.
But that is also a force of nature.
Wow, that's amazing...
Reminiscent?
Yes, it does.
I don't really like to come here.
But...
I'm with Taka, so I'm fine.
If you don't answer, I won't come.
Oh, my...
It's amazing.
You know, we decided to get rid of it once.
Oh, I see.
This police box...
But the junior high school students, the junior high school students at that time
They asked us to leave it.
I mean, we could clean up the whole women's side.
But if these things are handed down to the future generations
If the junior high school students were told that our future children
they would leave it behind.
Hmmm...
I see, but...
It's definitely painful for those who actually suffered from the disaster, like you, Mr. Takamatsu, to see it.
I guess it's hard to see, but it does make you remember.
But in a way, when you are working on reconstruction, you can forget about such things. While we are working on reconstruction, we can forget about such things.
This, the ground, that thing, that's there.
That's it, right there. That's it.
So, this, this round thing stuck in the ground.
I may have never seen it this close up before.
Ah, yes.
I had never seen a broken building like this before, where the building was actually falling and damaged.
It was very vivid, wasn't it?
Yes, it was.Yes.
Yes.
They say, "There was a tsunami," or "80% of the buildings were lost," but in reality, if you look at the bottom of the building, you can see the bottom of the building.
But when you actually look at the bottom of the building, at the bottom of the building...
It is a bit shocking.
It's very realistic to see what happened.
If you are not good at it, you are in the world of newspapers and TV.
People in Tokyo, for example. Yes, that's right.
The earthquake. Yes.
But if people could see this kind of thing when they come to Onagawa...
I'm a local and a participant in the disaster, so it's hard for me to say, "Okay, let's go there.
But the significance of this place is that it is exactly as the junior high school children lived it at that time.
But the significance of this place is that it is exactly as the junior high school children lived it back then.
But it is because of them that we are here today.
It was only a little over 10 years ago that a new town was being built.
It happened pretty fast, didn't it? Yes.
But I can see that Onagawa has evolved at an amazing speed.
But last time I was here, I told you that Onagawa had been cleaned up so much.
But the last time I was here, I heard that the reconstruction itself was still in its infancy.
I was reminded once again of the magnitude of what had happened, or how terrible it was.
I was reminded of the magnitude of what had happened, and how terrible it was.
It made me realize how terrible it was at that time.
We don't want to be called victims of the disaster forever.
We are a fish cake shop, so we have to reopen the fish cake shop.
We have people who work there, get paid there, work by themselves, eat by themselves, and wear clothes.
I work by myself, eat by myself, buy my own clothes
And then wash the water with a water supply cones.
I realized how hard a fight it was to regain that normalcy.
I really learned how hard it is to get back to the norm.
It's normal, isn't it? It's obvious, but it's hard work to get it back.
No one can tell you that the area where you live is safe.
That's why, in the aftermath of the earthquake and tsunami, when there was debris everywhere, Rain-chan and Momokuro were performing live.
Rain and Momokuro did a live concert in a place covered with debris after the earthquake.
They brought a lot of their fans, Monokunos, to the place that was covered with debris after the earthquake.
It was a great opportunity for us to see Onagawa as it was then.
We were very grateful to have the opportunity to see Onagawa as it was then.
We wondered how the town would change, because it would not get any worse.
I wondered how the town would change.
People will regain their normality again.
There is a fish market, and you see seagulls flying there now, right?
They are flying around a lot.
You know, it is strictly forbidden to fly there.
The market was destroyed right after the earthquake, so there were no landings because no boats could enter.
There was not a single bird.
Was it one?
Even though that village is doing it now.
The landings started coming in again, and the fish were so good, like samamaru and sabamaru, they were coming back.
And then they come back.
They're after them.
I didn't see a single bird.
They are strictly forbidden.
They like our fish, too.
But I was shocked when I had a seafood bowl in Onagawa.
I was shocked at how delicious it was.
It is hard to eat kaisendon outside of Onagawa.
That's what I am often told.
When I eat Okase-san's Onagawa donburi in Onagawa
I had the best time of my life at that moment.
But the kaisendon I eat afterwards makes me unhappy in comparison.
Happiness and the greatest unhappiness.
There are so many people.
There are a lot of people here.
What's that?
There's a face I've seen before.
You look like you're having a good time.
No, thank you.
Thank you.
How's it going?
I don't know.
I'm wrong? My...
Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you.
Hey, wait a minute.
What are you doing?
Just a minute.
Friend of yours?
Friend?
Wait a minute.
Our...
Our junior.
Thank you.
From Tohoku.
Galen from Chiba
Hello
Please enjoy Japan
Wait, what's going on here?
It's so cute!
I wish I could use one of these.
But it's charging, right?
Yes, it is.